wonder by RJ palasio part two via far above the world
planet earth is blue and There’s nothing I can do David Bowie Space
odity a tour of the Galaxy AUGUST IS THE Sun. Me and Mom and Dad are planets
orbiting the Sun. The rest of our family and friends are asteroids and comets
floating around the planets orbiting the Sun. The only celestial body that doesn’t
orbit August the Sun is Daisy the dog, and that’s only because to her little
doggy eyes, August’s face doesn’t look very different from any other human’s
face. To Daisy, all our faces look alike, as flat and pale as the
moon. I’m used to the way this universe works. I’ve never minded it because it’s
all I’ve ever known. I’ve always understood that August is special and
has special needs. If I was playing too loudly and he was trying to take a nap, I
knew I would have to play something else because he needed his rest after some
procedure or other had left him weak and in pain. If I wanted Mom and Dad to watch
me play soccer, I knew that nine out of 10 times they’d miss it because they
were busy shuttling August a speech therapy or physical therapy or a new
specialist or a surgery. Mom and Dad would always say I was the most
understanding little girl in the world. I don’t know about that, just that I
understood there was no point in complaining. I’ve seen August after his
surgeries: his little face bandaged up and swollen, his tiny body full of IVs
and tubes to keep him alive. After you’ve seen someone else going through that, it
feels kind of crazy to complain over not getting the toy you had asked for, or
your mom missing a school play. I knew this even when I was six years old. No
one ever told it to me. I just knew it. So
I’ve gotten used to not complaining, and I’ve gotten used to not bothering Mom
and Dad with little stuff. I’ve gotten used to figuring things out on my own:
how to put toys together, how to organize my life so I don’t miss friends’ birthday
parties had to stay on top of my schoolwork so I never fall behind in
class. I’ve never asked for a help with my homework. Never needed reminding to
finish a project or study for a test. If I was having trouble with a subject in
school, I’d go home and study it until I
figured it out on my own. I taught myself how to convert fractions into decimal
points by going online. I’ve done every school project pretty much by myself.
When Mom or Dad asked me how things are going in school, I’ve always said “good”—
”—even when it hasn’t always been so good.
My worst day, worst fall, worst headache, worst bruise, worst cramp, worst mean
thing anyone could say has always been nothing compared to what August has gone
through. This isn’t me being noble, by the
way: it’s just the way I know it is. And
this is the way it’s always been for me, for the little universe of us. But this
year there seems to be a shift in the cosmos. The galaxy is changed in Planets
are falling out of alignment before August I HONESTLY DON’T
remember my life before August came into it. I look at pictures of me as a baby,
and I see Mom and Dad smiling so happily, holding me. I can’t believe how much
younger they looked back then: Dad was this hipster dude and Mom was this cute Brazilian
fashionista. There’s one shot of me at my third birthday: Dad’s right behind me
while Mom’s holding the cake with three lit candles, and in back of us are Tata
and papa GRS Uncle Ben, Aunt Kate, and Uncle Po. Everyone’s looking at me and
I’m looking at the cake. You can see in that picture how I really was the first
child, first grandchild, first niece. I don’t remember what it felt like, of
course, but I can see it plain as can be
in the pictures. I don’t remember the day they brought August home from theal
hospital. I don’t remember what I said or
did or felt when I saw him for the first time, though everyone has a story about
it. Apparently, I just looked at him for a long time without saying anything at all,
and then finally I said: “It doesn’t look like
Lily That was the name of a doll GRS had given me when Mom was pregnant so I
could “practice” being a big sister. It was one of those dolls that are incredibly
lifelike, and I had carried it everywhere for months, changing its diaper, feeding
it. I’m told I even made a baby sling for
it. The story goes that after my initial reaction to August, it only took a few
minutes (according to gr's or a few days (according to Mom) before I was all over
him: kissing him, cuddling him, baby talking to him. After that I never so
much as touched or mentioned Lily ever again seeing August I NEVER USED to see August
the way other people saw him. I knew he didn’t look exactly normal, but I really
didn’t understand why strangers seemed so shocked when they saw him. Horrified.
Sickened.
Scared. There are so many words I can use to describe the looks on people’s faces.
And for a long time I didn’t get it. I’d
just get mad. Mad when they stared.
Mad when they looked away. “What the heck are you looking at?” I’d say to people— —even
grown-ups. Then, when I was about 11 I went to stay with gr's and monok for 4
weeks while August was having his big jaw surgery. This was the longest I’d
ever been away from home, and I have to say it was so amazing to suddenly be
free of all that stuff that made me so
mad. No one stared at gr and me when we went to town to buy groceries. No one
pointed at us. No one even noticed us gr was one of those grandmothers who do
everything with their grandkids. She’d run into the ocean if I asked her to,
even if she had nice clothes on. She would let me play with her makeup and
didn’t mind if I used it on her face to practice my face painting skills. She’d
take me for ice cream even if we hadn’t eaten dinner yet she draw chalk horses
on the sidewalk in front of her house.
One night, while we were walking back from town, I told her that I wished I
could live with her forever. I was so happy there. I think it might have been
the best time in my life. Coming home after 4 weeks felt very strange at first.
I remember very vividly stepping through the door and seeing August running over
to welcome me home, and for this tiny fraction of a moment I saw him not the
way I’ve always seen him, but the way other people see him. It was only a flash,
an instant while he was hugging me, so happy that I was home, but it surprised
me because I’d never seen him like that before. And I never felt what I was
feeling before, either: a feeling I hated myself for having the moment I had it.
But as he was kissing me with all his heart, all I could see was the drool
coming down his chin. And suddenly there I was, like all those people who would
stare or look away. Horrified. Sickened.
Scared. Thankfully, that only lasted for a second: the moment I heard August laughed
his raspy little laugh, it was over.
Everything was back the way it had been before. But it had opened a door for me. A
little peephole. And on the other side of the peephole there were two Augusts: the
one I saw blindly, and the one other people saw. I think the only person in
the world I could have told any of this
to was gr's but I didn’t. It was too hard to explain over the phone. I thought
maybe when she came for Thanksgiving, I’d tell her what I felt. But just two months
after I stayed with her in mon talk my beautiful Grands died. It was so
completely out of the blue. Apparently, she had checked herself into the
hospital because she’d been feeling nauseous. Mom and I drove out to see her,
but it’s a 3-hour drive from where we live, and by the time we got to the
hospital GRS was gone. A heart attack, they told us. Just like
that. It’s so strange how one day you can
be on this earth, and the next day not.
Where did she go? Will I really ever see her again, or is that a fairy tale? You
see movies and TV shows where people receive horrible news in hospitals, but
for us, with all our mini trips to the hospital with August, there had always
been good outcomes. What I remember the most from the day gr's died is Mom
literally crumbling to the floor in slow, heaving sobs, holding her stomach like
someone had just punched her. I’ve never, ever seen Mom like that. Never heard
sounds like that come out of her. Even through all of August’s surgeries, Mom
always put on a brave face. On my last
day in mon talk gr and I had watched the sunset on the beach. We had taken a
blanket to sit on, but it had gotten chilly, so we wrapped it around us and
cuddled and talked until there wasn’t even a sliver of sun left over the ocean.
And then gr told me she had a secret to tell me: she loved me more than anyone
else in the world. “Even August?” I had asked. She smiled and stroked my hair,
like she was thinking about what to say.
“I love aie very, very much,” she said softly. I can still remember her
Portuguese accent, the way she rolled her arms that he has many angels looking up
for him already, Via. And I want you to know that you have me looking out for
you Okay Manina Kar I want you to know that you are number one for me. You are
my She looked out at the ocean and spread her hands
like she was trying to smooth out the waves, “You are my everything. You understand me, Via
to I understood her. And I knew why she said it was a secret. Grandmothers aren’t
supposed to have favorites. Everyone knows that. But after she died, I held on
to that secret and let it cover me like a blanket August through the
people HIS eyes EYES ARE about an inch below where they should be on his face,
almost to halfway down his cheeks. They slant downward at an extreme angle,
almost like diagonal slits that someone cut into his face, and the left one is
noticeably lower than the right one. They bulge outward because his eye cavities
are too shallow to accommodate them. The top eyelids are always halfway closed,
like he’s on the verge of sleeping. The lower eyelids sag so much they almost
look like a piece of invisible string is pulling them downward: you can see the
red part on the inside, like they’re almost inside out. He doesn’t have
eyebrows or eyelashes. His nose is disproportionately big for his face, and
kind of fleshy. His head is pinched in on the sides where the ears should be, like
someone used giant pliers and crush the middle part of his face. He doesn’t have
cheekbones. There are deep creases running down both sides of his nose to
his mouth, which gives him a waxy appearance. Sometimes people assume he’s
been burned in a fire: his features look like they’ve been melted, like the
drippings on the side of a candle.
Several surgeries to correct his pallet have left a few scars around his mouth,
the most noticeable one being a jagged gash running from the middle of his
upper lip to his nose. His upper teeth are small and splay out. He has a severe
overbite and an extremely undersized jawbone. He has a very small chin. When he
was very little, before a piece of his hipbone was surgically implanted into
his lower jaw, he really had no chin at all. His tongue would just hang out of
his mouth with nothing underneath to block it. Thankfully, it’s better now. He
can eat, at least: when he was younger, he had a feeding tube. And he can talk. And
he’s learned to keep his tongue inside his mouth, though that took him several
years to master. He’s also learned to control the drool that used to run down
his neck. These are considered miracles.
When he was a baby, the doctors didn’t think he’d live. He can hear, too. Most
kids born with these types of birth defects have problems with their middle
ears that prevent them from hearing, but so far August can hear well enough
through his tiny caulif flower shaped ears. The doctors think that eventually
he’ll need to wear hearing aids, though.
August hates the thought of this. He thinks the hearing aids will get noticed
too much. I don’t tell him that the hearing aids would be the least of his
problems, of course, because I’m sure he knows this. Then again, I’m not really
sure what August knows or doesn’t know, what he understands and doesn’t
understand. Does August see how other people see him, or has he gotten so good
at pretending not to see that it doesn’t bother him? Or does it bother him? When he
looks in the mirror, does he see the Auggie Mom and Dad see, or does he see
the Auggie everyone else sees? Or is there another August he sees, someone in
his dreams behind the misshapen head and face? Sometimes when I look at GRS I can
see the pretty girl she used to be underneath the wrinkles. I could see the
girl from impanema inside the old lady walk. Does August see himself as he might
have looked without that single gene that caused the catastrophe of his face?
I wish I could ask him this stuff. I wish
he would tell me how he feels. He used to be easier to read before the surgeries.
You knew that when his eyes squinted, he was happy. When his mouth went straight,
he was being mischievous. When his cheeks trembled, he was about to cry. He looks
better now, no doubt about that, but the signs we used to gauge his moods are all
gone. There are new ones, of course. Mom and Dad can read every single one. But
I’m having trouble keeping up. And there’s a part of me that doesn’t want
to keep trying: why can’t he just say what he’s feeling like everyone else? He
doesn’t have a trig tube in his mouth anymore that keeps him from talking. His
Jaws not wired shut. He’s 10 years old. He can use his words. But we circle around
around him like he’s still the baby he
used to be. We change plans, go to plan B, interrupt conversations, go back on
promises depending on his moods, his whims, his needs. That was fine when he
was little. But he needs to grow up now.
We need to let him, help him, make him
grow up. Here’s what I think: we’ve all spent so much time trying to make August
think he’s normal that he actually thinks he is normal. And the problem is, he’s not
[Music]